once you've got a trade open and
especially when it's in profit there are
a whole bunch of decisions that you have
to make but among those there's one
important decision that I make each time
that I think gets overlooked by most
Traders the decision is about which
approach to take when closing the trade
in profit and this should be based on
what's most logical for the type of
opportunity I'm trading I broadly put
this into two categories I can either
take a defensive or an offensive
approach now in general what I see from
most Traders is that they'll have a bias
for one particular exit approach
sometimes this is dictated by their
trading system for example they might
always take multiple partials at
different key levels sometimes they
don't even make the decision ahead of
time and they just leave it to their gut
feeling or emotions like when they get
nervous loss aversion kicks in and they
grab the profit while they still can and
a lot of the time it's based on people's
risk tolerance so more risk averse
people will be defensive and risk SE
will be more aggressive instead just
like how I approach all areas of my
trading I think there should be some
logic behind the decision you know most
Traders only think about their trading
strategy in terms of the criteria they
need to enter a trade but you should
also think about the strategy you're
using to execute manage and exit the
trade and that strategy should change
based on the opportunity so I want to
explain to you the logic that I use and
then you can decide whether this is
something that you want to adopt for
your own Trading and I'd be delighted if
you do and I'd love to hear about it in
the comment section down below any
changes that you've chosen to make you
know this approach is not complicated
it's actually really simple but the idea
here the idea of this video and the
channel in general is to help you to be
more conscious and more logical about
the decisions that you make with your
trading so first let me give you a quick
highlevel overview of an important
aspect of my trading when I enter a
trade I'm not doing that because I
believe that individual trade will be
profitable
instead I'm entering a trade when an
opportunity has a positive expectancy
above a particular margin of error and I
figure this out by assessing the
potential outcomes and then estimating
the probabilities of each of those
outcomes happening so for the first
order outcomes one will be negative and
would put me into a loss and the other
would be positive and put me into a
profit then from that point onwards
after entering the trade my trade
management decisions are mostly based on
the same I assess the next potential
outcomes and estimate the probabilities
of those so that way I have an idea of
the expectancy and I can take an
appropriate action based on that and I
believe that this is the most logical
way to make trading decisions now
there's obviously a lot more to it than
just that but that's just a brief bit of
background info to help you follow along
with this video and if you want to
understand more about this and how to
apply it to your own trading check out
the link in the description there's a
video there for you so let's say I'm in
a profitable trade and the price has
completed the the first order outcome I
know that this is an area where there's
likely to be a shift in activity which
means there's a higher risk at this
point that the price may move against me
so at this point the action I take will
differ depending on whether I've chosen
a defensive or offensive approach for
exiting the trade a defensive approach
means I want to protect my Capital as
much as possible including the profit
that I've built up on this open position
whereas an offensive approach means I'm
willing to R risk more of that profit
for the potential of earning an even
bigger return so let's think about why
there might be a difference we know that
even when the price is moving heavily in
a profitable direction for us most of
the time there will still be moments
when the price moves against us that's
just part of the price Discovery process
sometimes it will be a minor fluctuation
but the longer you hold a trade for the
more chance there is for entire moves
against you to put it in simple terms if
you're in a bearish trend and you have
low highs those are Still Moments where
the price was moving against you for a
prolonged period of time and you had to
make a decision whether to hold on to
the trade or not so for a defensive
approach I'm making the decision that I
don't want to wait for one of those
pullbacks against me I'd rather close
the trade and bank that profit now this
would be appropriate for situations
where the expectancy on the next
potential outcomes is much lower and it
no longer makes sense to take that risk
it shouldn't just be based on how I feel
and loss of cersion and things like that
it should be based on the logic of the
opportunity on the other hand if I'm
taking an offensive approach I'm willing
to stay in the trade but that doesn't
mean that I want to allow the price to
move all the way against me until all
the profit is wiped out instead I'm
going to move my stop order into a
profitable position so I'm allowing the
price to move against me to a certain
extent to have its pull back before
continuing the next move in the
direction I want it to but any further
than that point and I'll be out of the
trade for a lower profit than I would
have had if I'd taken the defensive
approach if I've taken that decision it
means that I believe the next potential
outcomes give a positive expectancy for
my trade now that part is relatively
straightforward the more tricky question
is where I should move my stop loss to
if it's too close the price might easily
trigger it before then moving where I
want it to but if it's too far away I'm
unnecessarily risking more of my profit
so that answer as always is to base it
on probabilities I want to move my stop
loss to the point where the probability
of it retesting my entry point is so
high that it's no longer viable to stay
in that trade any longer in other words
it's the point where the expectancy for
staying in the trade beyond that is
negative so beyond that point it's no
longer logical to be holding that risk
therefore I need to be actively
analyzing the markets even after the
point of entry now that doesn't mean
that I need to analyze every single
price tick it just means I need to
identify where there are levels or areas
that may cause a shift in activity in
the markets meaning a change in the
balance between volume and liquidity by
identifying those areas it allows me to
estimate the probabilities of different
potential price moves and again just
like I mentioned earlier if you want to
understand that side of things in much
more detail check the link below for the
free training it's beyond the scope of
this video otherwise this would end up
being over an hour long but you know
things always sound great in theory but
the thing about the markets is that
things aren't always black and white
sometimes you might need to start with
an offensive approach and after certain
price movements take place you then
switch to a more defensive approach in
fact that's what happens most often when
you get those huge runaway trades that
have a huge profit where you're just
Rising the trend and sometimes an
opportunity will call for a mix of both
both approaches at the same time for
example let's go through a recent trade
that I took on pound Yen so you can see
it here the price was in a shortterm
range and the situation met my criteria
for a short trade entry towards the top
I had positive expectancy but the
situation wasn't entirely
straightforward you see at this time all
Yen pairs were slowly grinding higher as
the Yen continued to weaken and I knew
there was a good chance that that would
continue so after the initial profitable
move if I had one I knew that any
pullbacks could be a signed that the
bullish trend is continuing and the
price would then break through my entry
point therefore putting me into a loss
but on the other hand there was also an
expectation in the market that at any
time Japanese policy makers could
intervene in the market to strengthen
the Yen as they had already done
recently there were loads of comments
coming out from policy makers saying
that they were concerned about the
situation with the Yen and they were
monitoring it for potential intervention
so if that did happen there would be a
huge bearish Surge and make a huge
profit so in this situation I decided to
split the trade and take both a
defensive and offensive Approach at the
same time and what happened next after I
entered the trade a comment came out
from a key policy maker suggesting once
again that they were considering
intervention and so pound Yen dropped
rapidly to my first key level at that
point after risking just 0.6% on the
trade initially that was the total
amount of risk I was already up over 2%
in profit so I split the trade one half
was short-term focused and the other
half was longer term focused the
short-term focused one was a defensive
approach so I closed it and banked a 1%
profit because there was a good chance
that the price would reverse from that
point and so it didn't make sense for
the short-term Market context to stay in
the trade if I was just focused on the
short term the expectancy wasn't high
enough there was too much risk so it's
best to to take a defensive approach and
take the profit then for the longer term
part of the trade I decided to take the
offensive approach so I kept the trade
open but moved my stop loss to break
even now moving the stop loss to break
even wasn't because that's where my
entry point was it's because that was
the point on the chart that I recognized
that activity could change in the market
so if the price got back to my entry
point the probability was high that it
would break through and therefore
continued to move higher but if it
didn't reach there the probability will
hire for a further move down into profit
for me now as you can see in the end the
price did reverse and eventually hit my
stop loss and broke through so I was
left with just the 1% profit that I
banked from the defensive approach on
the shortterm part of the trade now
that's just one simple example but in
different situations with different
context different levels different
opportunities the logic will change
rather than having a set and forget
approach where I just open a trade and
wait for it to hit my profit Target and
hopefully the best I'm tailoring my
strategy around what's right for the
opportunity and in fact that same
approach that I explained to you with
pound Yen I was doing that all of the
time with the different Yen Pairs and I
was explaining it to our members waiting
for that big bearish move to happen and
as you can see from the chart behind me
recently it did happen so I just take
that approach over and over again if the
context is showing that it's right to do
that if I get the signal for a
short-term entry then I'll enter the
trade once the trade is in profit I can
then split the time Horizons be
defensive on one part and aggressive
with the other part and I'll slowly
build a positive return on the
short-term position and still have the
chance for a runaway trade when Japan
takes action on the other part of the
trade you know as I said before it's not
complicated it's actually very simple
but the important part here is about
using the probabilities and the
expectancy of the situation to make the
most logical decisions rather than just
taking a blanket set and forget approach
for all trades in just the exact same
way and if you want more examples of
different situations or to understand
the other decisions that I make with my
trade management let me know by hitting
the like button on the video and leaving
a comment below things don't have to be
complicated but they should always be
logical and hopefully I can encourage
you to start thinking that way too